There Is No Inherent Right and Wrong.
The Reason for Precepts.
When a bird sees the United States
invading Iraq,
would it know whether it's right or wrong?
Would a dog know whether
it's right or wrong?
Our minds define what is right and wrong.
All existence in this world
only just exist.
A rock is just a rock and gold is just gold.
It is just our thoughts that
the gold is more expensive
and valuable than a rock.
This is mine and that is yours is
also just our thoughts.
This woman is mine and that woman is
yours is also only our thoughts.
Outside of our consciousness,
there is no right or wrong,
no good or bad,
and no pureness or filth in this world.
Don't you think so?
It's only our minds that give these distinctions.
It is just our thought that something is
right or wrong.
Where is the objective proof of something
being right or wrong?
When you say, this is mine, that, too,
is but your thought.
Where is the proof that
it is actually yours?
(Questioner) I am sorry to interrupt,
(Questioner) but may I ask a question?
(Sunim) Please do.
(Questioner) As a result of the war,
(Questioner) many innocent Iraqis died.
(Questioner) How can we explain that?
Is it okay that even greater number of
worms and plankton
die because of human beings?
When we try to thwart SARS virus,
it's a big problem from the
virus's position.
When we kill mosquitoes during summer,
from the mosquitoes' position,
it's a big problem.
Thus, from the fundamental
principle's position,
it's only a point of view.
It's the same between married
couples and between countries.
In the fundamental sense,
there is no right or wrong.
There is only the fact.
The question is what will you choose?
Not what's right or wrong.
it is about 'what will you choose?'
For example, you see something.
You wanted it, so you took it.
There is no problem.
Since you took it,
you were jailed as a thief.
If you can accept it as an inevitable
consequence, that is fine.
But, you will regret it after being in
jail for 6 months for stealing.
That's where the problem is.
The problem doesn't lie in the fact
that you stole it.
As I mentioned before,
the problem is in your mind.
The problem lies in the fact that
you regret stealing while
you spend 6 months in jail.
Let's say there is a pretty lady.
I hug her because I want to.
Many people cuss me out
and say 'this monk is crazy'.
Despite all the cussing,
if I say 'Wow! I got to hug her.
I feel great.'
(Audience Laughter)
Then it's okay.
But when I hear all that criticism,
I regret it.
And I would resent them.
'Do I deserve so much loathing
just for hugging her?'
'You people do it all the time'
(Audience Laughter)
So it brings me pain.
That's why it's a foolish act.
In Buddhism, there is no right or wrong.
We say the action is foolish.
We say a murder is a foolish action.
Let's say you murdered someone.
On the flip side, if someone murder you,
you would hold a grudge, right?
Then, you would want to revenge, right?
Not only yourself, but if your parent,
siblings, friends, or countrymen
got killed, you would want to avenge
them, right? you would, wouldn't you?
So, when you get killed by
an act of revenge,
and you think 'Since I killed someone,
I deserve to die too',
then it's okay.
But people don't think that killing others is
the same as being killed themselves.
Even if they have killed 10,000 people,
they don't want to die.
They would spare 10,000 people
so they could live.
So the consequence of an act of
murder is regret.
It's the same for stealing,
fighting and lying.
Simply put, when you plant one seed,
you don't just get one fruit,
but 100 or even 1,000.
The result of one's action
comes back 100 or 1000 folds.
That's why we think it's unfair.
We all think life is unfair.
There is nothing that comes back to us
which we have not caused.
But everyone thinks life is unfair.
Why is that?
It's because the seeds of the causal
relationship come back.
So you are better off not
choosing such actions.
It is foolish to do such a thing.
That's why Buddha said
'Don't kill, Don't steal,'
'Don't fight, Don't lie'
Let's say you saw someone drowning.
So you used a stick and
helped him out of the water.
It wasn't that difficult for you,
but the person rescued would be
immensely grateful.
Helping someone when he falls,
helping someone from drowning,
or helping someone
who can help himself,
the level of their gratitude in all these
3 cases would be different, or not?
(Audience) They are different.
Even though your actions were the same,
the drowning person you saved
that seed you planted in
relation to that person
would bear 1000 fruit.
Thus, saving a life of a living being
is the greatest virtue.
This Buddhist principle can be
applied to everything.
If I offer to carry your luggage as
you are going down the stairs,
you would be thankful
but it wouldn't bring you to tears.
(Audience Laughter)
Last time when I was climbing up to
go to BongJung Temple,
my legs were in so much pain that I could
hardly move. If someone had offered to
carry my luggage
would I have been thankful or not?
I would be so grateful that I would cry.
If you buy me a $30 dinner now,
I would not be that thankful.
(Audience Laughter)
Back when I was traveling penniless,
when someone offered me
even just a bowl of rice,
I was so grateful that the tears
would roll down my face.
Now when I go to a temple
and nobody gives me food, I feel fine.
Because I can just go out and
buy my own meal.
But when I was traveling penniless,
I went to a temple
and they did not give me any food.
I was so hurt.
(Audience Laughter)
So, a same act, depending on the circumstance,
can result in a very different way.
So, among the foolish acts,
killing brings the worst consequence,
taking what is not yours is next,
the third is sexual misconduct,
and the fourth is lying.
Which is better?
Some stranger fondling
your breasts and kissing you
...
(Audience Laughter)
or someone cursing at you?
Cursing is better, right?
So these precepts exist in order.
Someone groping your bottom is distressing,
but having $100 stolen from you would be worse.
(Audience Laughter)
It's better than your money being stolen.
Even though material possessions are
valuable,
when there is a knife at your throat,
would you hand him your diamond ring
or let him kill you? (Audience Laughter)
You would give him the ring.
Material possessions are less
valuable than your life.
You would normally explode
if you found out that your husband
was having an affair.
But if your husband would earn $10000
by spending a night with another woman,
of course not all women would, but
some of you may say
'Well, it's Sunday.
Since you are not doing anything...
you can go'
(Audience Laughter)
That's why people can sell sex for money.
It's important, but it's after
money in the order.
So, though not explicitly stated,
The precepts are listed in the
order of importance.
So higher on the list, greater the karmic results.
So, when you get angry,
you might cuss but refrain from
sexual misconduct.
You should not steal.
and you should absolutely not kill.
Do not make foolish mistakes.
It would be like stealing a dime, a small
mistake, but having to pay back $10.
It’s foolish, so, don't do it.
These are the precepts.
So, the United States invading Iraq
is a foolish act.
Why? If they spent 1/10 of the war funds
to help the needy,
they would have good fortune coming back
in multiples.
US is attacking Iraq
for the benefit of acquiring oil for now,
but eventually
the whole population of Muslims
will react to it as an attack on Islam.
The populations of Iraq is a
few tens of millions
but the total Islamic populations
is 1.3 billion.
So even though the US did benefit
by taking $100 billion worth of oil,
now the Americans are in fear working
in tall buildings,
as well as on the airplanes.
They need to fear the invisible terrors
that require them to deploy
air marshals on planes and many other
security systems everywhere.
The loss is greater for
Americans ultimately.
Furthermore, the US power and
the moral authority
that dominated the world till now
have been challenged by
the rest of the world.
By losing the legitimacy,
the US has fallen as a gangster
nation, even with its power
All the respect that the US and
the Americans used to have
are now in jeopardy because
the US resorts to violence.
This means that its position of
authority has hit the limit.
It has not gone this far before,
but its use of violence means that
its power has now reached the limit.
Like a husband who resorts
to beating his wife,
he is up against a wall.
The US is now in crisis and
is in a downward spiral.
Putting it bluntly,
the Americans are to be pitied now.
They are being very foolish.
The negative consequences
do not appear immediately.
It takes time and comes back slowly.
In this sense, this war is unjust.
It is foolish.
This is how we see things.
Hussein was a dictator in Iraq.
So, he wasn't a good person, right?
But Hussein being a bad person
and the US invading Iraq are
two separate issues.
A monk disobeys the precepts,
has love affairs,
and accumulates wealth.
It is a separate issue punishing him
by the Korean laws.
Why? Because all Korean citizens
have the right
to marry, to date,
and to accumulate wealth. right?
(Audience) yes
yes
So the monk is not subject to such
legal punishment.
But as the monk who pledged
to follow the precepts
in our religious order,
we can criticize that monk.
Likewise, the Iraqi people can protest
against Hussein's regime,
but the US has no legitimate reason
to invade Iraq.
Even if Hussein had those weapons
of mass destruction.
So, you must not misunderstand this
about North Korea.
It is foolish that Kim Jong Il
produces nuclear weapons
while his people are dying of hunger.
It is foolish for him to let his people
dying of starvation.
And we must criticize him.
But, the US has no legitimate reason to
bomb North Korea.
These are separate issues.
This is a nation to nation issues.
The US produces missiles,
develops nuclear weapons,
and sells these thing all
over the world.
The North Korea, too,
can make missiles, nuclear weapons
and sell them to other countries.
But, North Koreans can criticize
and we can criticize these things
about North Korea
but US has no right to criticize
the North Korea.
So, the US's actions are unjust.
It's unreasonable.
It means that it is a foolish act.
Why? The foolish actions will bring about
undesirable consequences.
The anti-American sentiment in
Korea is such.
So, when we are involved in the
peace movement,
if we think, he is a bad guy,
the anger arises.
This thought generates anger.
But instead if we think, He is a foolish
guy, How do we feel?
There is no anger.
He is a bad guy and I have to change him,
this thought can drive us to fight
in power struggle.
If we think
'He is foolish. We need to awake him',
then we can handle him without struggle.
So, we must carry out our peace movement,
without anger within us.
From this point of view, there is
inherently no right and wrong.
If someone is naked, we can't say that
it is wrong.
One is naked here,
and another one naked
in the bath house.
Being naked in itself is neither
right nor wrong.
According to convention,
being naked in the bath house does what?
It does not offend anybody, right?
But here if someone is naked,
it would offend people, right?
So, we say that it is a foolish act.
Don't do such an act.
In reality, there is no inherent
good or evil.
But there are actions that are
foolish or wise.
So, in Buddhism, we say that the foolish
actions are to be avoided.
That's what we can say.